<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vulvectomy on CU Pathology</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/vulvectomy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vulvectomy on CU Pathology</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2024 Richard Revia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/vulvectomy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vulvectomy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/vulvectomy/vulvectomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/vulvectomy/vulvectomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross Description&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orient the specimen as if viewed in situ. Look for orientation sutures provided by the surgeon&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use 4 colors to ink peripheral margins including the underlying/deep aspect of each quadrant (*use &amp;ldquo;clockface&amp;rdquo; inking in quadrants in case you need to go back to the specimen). (The deep margin should NOT get its own separate color but should be inked according to quadrant colors.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Measure the specimen in three dimensions, describe the color and size of all surface lesions, and section with full thickness incisions perpendicular to the skin surface. Measure all subcutaneous lesions including greatest depth of invasion and distances to 2 closest margins.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take a gross photos, including a cross section of tumor if one is grossly visible&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sequentially slice the specimen and number the slices (ex: The specimen is sequentially sectioned into 12 slices from 12:00 to 6:00.) For any submitted section, consider noting the slice # (+/- the o’clock position) in the casette key and annotating the gross photo to indicate specifically where you took sections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If additional tissue is present, dissect the inguinal tissue and look for lymph nodes. Keep right and left separate and note laterality in slide key.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for Histology:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Maximum thickness of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tumor in relation to nearest peripheral, mucosal, and deep margins&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How to take tips is somewhat case dependent. Ideally, discuss with your attending, an experienced senior resident, or a PA. Whatever approach you use, describe it precisely in the gross description&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examples:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Perpendicular&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;En face&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tips bisected and non-inked side down in cassette&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Be sure to provide a gross distance from tumor to margin at the tips&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If blocking out tissue or submitting a continuous section across multiple casettes, note this with “in tandem” or “in continuity.” When in doubt, consult the attending.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Additional lesions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All lymph nodes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Uninvolved skin including clitoris, fourchette, perineum, contra-lateral labia majora and minora, depending on what is available and able to be oriented&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the entire specimen fits in 20 or fewer cassettes, submit entirely; otherwise, CALL YOUR ATTENDING&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-reports&#34;&gt;Example Reports&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;sample-1&#34;&gt;Sample #1&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Designated &amp;ldquo;XXXXX&amp;rdquo; is an oriented, tan-pink, wrinkled elliptical skin excision measuring 1.8 x 0.6 cm, excised to a depth of 0.2 cm. There is a suture designated &amp;ldquo;12:00&amp;rdquo;. The surface has an ill-defined, white-pink, nodular mass (1.4 x 0.4 cm), which is grossly 0.4 cm to the 12:00 edge, &amp;lt;0.1 cm to the 3:00 edge, involves the 6:00 edge, and &amp;lt;0.1 cm to the 9:00 edge. Inking is as follows: 12:00-3:00 = Red, 3:00-6:00 = Yellow, 6:00-9:00 = Green, 9:00-12:00 = Blue.&#xA;The specimen is serially sectioned from 12:00-6:00 and is entirely and sequentially submitted as follows:&lt;/br&gt;&#xA;(C1) 12:00 tip, bisected&lt;/br&gt;&#xA;(C2-C3) Central cross-sections&lt;/br&gt;&#xA;(C4) 6:00 edge, en face&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
