<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CU Pathology</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on CU Pathology</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2024 Richard Revia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stoma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/g1/intestine/stoma/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/g1/intestine/stoma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Headers:&lt;/strong&gt; “Stoma, ileostomy:”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;triage-needed&#34;&gt;Triage Needed:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;None, usually received in formalin.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;procedure&#34;&gt;Procedure:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Document the specimen as it was received (overall measurements) and describe what is present (skin, protruding mucosa, viable/normal bowel, and/or any lesions or abnormalities).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove the staple line and put the margin en face in a cassette.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A perpendicular section through the stoma to include the exposed mucosa, relationship to the peripheral skin, and mucosa deep to the opening. This can be completed in one section provided there are no lesions or abnormalities.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If lesions and/or abnormalities are present, these must be described, measured, and the distance to the peripheral and bowel margin are required for microscopic examination. Note if this patient has a history of a variety of cancers in the abdomen, the most likely site for a metastasis is along the periphery of the specimen and less likely on the mucosal surface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The margin needs to be submitted along with a section through the stoma in two cassettes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These specimens are often removed when there is revision surgery, the stoma needs to be moved, or the bowels are reconnected, and the stoma is no longer necessary. Aside from documentation of the ileostomy specimen, the gross exam should include the condition of the stoma and mucosa to make sure the bowel was not incarcerated or dusky. The viability of the mucosal margin needs to be confirmed and ensure there is no pathology on the mucosal surface and along the periphery of the soft tissues and bowel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mastectomy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/breast/mastectomy/mastectomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:52 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/breast/mastectomy/mastectomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To ensure proper key characteristics, measurements and sampling occur in the grossing of breast specimens (partial/simple/skin sparing/nipple sparing/modified radical/radical mastectomy, etc.) please take note of the following considerations, required sections, and template below. ALL cancer breasts need to be scanned in the Faxitron and images used for clip localization and confirmation. The prophylactic side can be bypassed if no clips/suspicion for bilateral disease.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indication: Cervical cancer</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_cervical_cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_cervical_cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;radical-hysterectomy-for-cervical-cancer&#34;&gt;Radical Hysterectomy for Cervical Cancer&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross description&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orient the uterus, weigh it, and differentially ink the anterior/posterior surfaces including the parametrial soft tissue&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove the parametrial tissue, perpendicularly section it, and submit each side (right, left) entirely (NOT JUST THE MARGINS)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Amputate the cervix and open it as you would a cone biopsy:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Describe the tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Measure the maximum tumor width, length and distance to nearest cervical margin and vaginal margin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the vaginal cuff:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If tumor is &amp;lt; 1 cm from the cuff, submit perpendicular sections of the tumor with margin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If tumor is &amp;gt; 1 cm from the cuff, submit shave margins&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Section the cervix longitudinally at 3 mm intervals and describe tumor depth:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Measure maximum wall thickness in this area&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If prior therapy has been done, no gross tumor may be seen&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cut the uterus into anterior and posterior halves:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Make transverse sections to examine the endometrium and myometrium&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take gross photos, ideally including a cross section of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for histology&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;cervix&#34;&gt;Cervix&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Parametrial tissue: collect bilateral samples and place in separate cassettes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If gross tumor is present:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;3 slices of tissue with full wall thickness in the deepest areas of invasion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 slice of uninvolved cervix (always designate o’clock position so that tumor size can be reconstructed at sign-out)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cervical cancer staging rests upon precise tumor measurements in multiple dimensions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Consider &lt;strong&gt;annotating a gross photograph&lt;/strong&gt; so that it is obvious where each section came from&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Make sure there is &lt;strong&gt;at least 1 section per cm&lt;/strong&gt; of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If no gross tumor present (e.g., after a cold knife cone):&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Entire cervix needs to be amputated and submitted radially (just like a cervical cone)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;uterine-corpus&#34;&gt;Uterine corpus&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2 transverse sections of &lt;strong&gt;lower uterine segment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Full-thickness &lt;strong&gt;anterior&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;posterior&lt;/strong&gt; endomyometrium in 1 cassette each&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;bilateral-fallopian-tubes-and-ovaries&#34;&gt;Bilateral fallopian tubes and ovaries&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If grossly normal, submit:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the left ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the right ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit the entire fimbriated ends of the fallopian tubes (perpendicularly sectioned) and at least 1 representative cross-section, separating left from right&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;lymph-nodes&#34;&gt;Lymph nodes&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For small nodes that will fix well, multiple per cassette submitted in toto &lt;strong&gt;OR&lt;/strong&gt; nodes inked and bisected (so we can tell microscopically which pieces of nodes belong together)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A good rule of thumb is to bisect lymph nodes if they are &amp;gt; 0.3 cm in greatest dimension&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the node is very fatty, make sure it is sectioned THINLY&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit extra fibroadipose tissue (up to 10 cassettes total)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;dictation-template&#34;&gt;Dictation template&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The specimen is received [fresh/for intraoperative consultation/in formalin], labeled &amp;ldquo;[name/MRN/designation]&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frozen Worksheet</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/breast/sentinel/sentinel_frozens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/breast/sentinel/sentinel_frozens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;breast-sentinel-lymph-node-frozen-worksheet&#34;&gt;Breast Sentinel Lymph Node Frozen Worksheet&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;at-the-time-of-the-frozen-section&#34;&gt;At the time of the frozen section:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gross measurement: ___ x ___ x ___ cm&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove all fat from individual lymph nodes&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Number of lymph nodes: ___&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Serially section each lymph node at 2 mm intervals along the long axis&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Embed all sections serially with non-adjacent cut surfaces face down&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; embed only grossly positive sections&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEEP or Cone</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/cervix/leep_cone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/cervix/leep_cone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross Description:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orient the specimen if an orienting stitch is provided (usually designated “stitch at 12:00”) and measure in three dimensions. If no orienting stitch is present, you do NOT need to arbitrarily designate anything as 12:00.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ink the rim of the endocervical margin blue and the remaining margin (deep/stromal, and ectocervical) black&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When possible, note the size in each dimension; the presence/diameter of an os&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Note the presence of absence of a mass or lesion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If a mass or lesion is present, note the size and distance to margins&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Make radial (like a pizza) serial sections at 2-3 mm intervals&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Note that these specimens range from well-oriented cervical cones with an identifiable os, ectocervix, and endocervical canal; to a LEEP fragment of tissue with no orientation and no identifiable landmarks. Please tailor the gross description accordingly. If there is an ectocervix/os, provide the diameter(s).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for histology:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit the entire specimen sequentially into cassettes (no more than 3 per cassette) with the 4 quadrants designated separately&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If a “top hat” (additional endocervix in a separate part) is present submit it separately. Check if the clinician has oriented the top hat, by designating the (true) margin, and if so, preserve the orientation through inking and gross description. If the clinician has not made any designation, no inking is required. Note, for the majority of top hat specimens, clinician input is required for orientation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sample-dictaiton-cervical-cone&#34;&gt;Sample dictaiton: &amp;ldquo;Cervical Cone&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Received in formalin container labeled “[patient&amp;rsquo;s name/ medical record number/&amp;quot;___&amp;quot;]” is a[n] [un]oriented fragment of tissue measuring [___x___x___] cm [___ cm ectocervix diameter; cervical wall thickness of ___; ___cm from ecto cervix into endocervical canal] with a stitch designating [12 o&amp;rsquo;clock]. [The cervical os measures ___ cm in diameter.] The overlying epithelium is [smooth and glistening without grossly visible lesions]. The endocervical margin is inked [blue] and the remaining margin inked [black]. [No masses or lesions are identified. / A mass measures ___ cm and is ___cm from the deep margin; ___ cm from the ectocervical mucosal margin; and ___ cm from the endocervical mucosal margin.] The specimen is divided into quadrants, serially sectioned and submitted entirely in cassettes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anastomoses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/g1/intestine/anastomoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/g1/intestine/anastomoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Headers:&lt;/strong&gt; “Ileum and Colon, Ileocolonic anastomosis, revision&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;triage-needed&#34;&gt;Triage Needed:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;None, if fresh (and no ancillary testing requested) can be placed in formalin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indication: Endometrial hyperplasia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_endometrial_hyperplasia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_endometrial_hyperplasia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;radical-hysterectomy-for-endometrial-hyperplasia&#34;&gt;Radical Hysterectomy for Endometrial Hyperplasia&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross description&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orient the uterus and weigh it&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ink the:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;anterior and posterior resection margins (not the serosa)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;parametrial tissue (only if present; will only be there for radical hysterectomy specimens)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove the bilateral parametrial/paracervical tissues (if present, usually only in cervical cancer cases) and perpendicularly section&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bivalve the uterus and take a gross photograph&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the cavity and mucosa and describe any lesions present&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Record the size, location, and appearance of the tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Serially section the entire endometrial cavity and describe the pattern of invasion (pushing, infiltrative, or discontinuous?)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Measure the greatest depth of invasion and the maximum myometrial thickness in this area&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Each case must have an average (uninvolved) endometrial thickness and myometrial thickness recorded&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take gross photos, including a cross section of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for histology&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;cervix&#34;&gt;Cervix&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the cervix is normal and there is no history of dysplasia:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take one section each of anterior and posterior cervix to include the squamocolumnar junction&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If there is a concurrent history of dysplasia:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 section per quadrant&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;uterine-corpus&#34;&gt;Uterine corpus&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lower anterior uterine segment:&#xA;- 1 longitudinal section each of &lt;strong&gt;anterior&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;posterior&lt;/strong&gt;, noting if there is tumor involvement&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Uterine body:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Frozen section remnant&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pilot tumor section (this only needs to be done if submission of sections is on the day following receipt of the specimen)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the specimen is received and completely grossed/submitted on the same day, no &amp;ldquo;pilot&amp;rdquo; is needed&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bilateral parametria (if present), serially sectioned and submitted entirely, separating left from right&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tumor:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit 2 full thickness slices of the uterine wall in the area where the tumor appears the deepest and&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2 additional superficial sections of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit additional sections of tumor such that you have at least 1 section of tumor per cm (if tumor is &amp;gt;4 cm)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Uninvolved endomyometrium:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 full thickness section each of anterior and posterior endomyometrium to demonstrate histology away from the tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If there is no lesion grossly visible:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit 1 full thickness section each of the anterior and posterior endomyometrium,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then, submit the remainder of the endometrium in superficial strips (usually 2-3/cassette)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;These should be deep enough to include the endomyometrial junction, but not the entire myometrium&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;bilateral-fallopian-tubes-and-ovaries&#34;&gt;Bilateral fallopian tubes and ovaries&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If grossly normal, submit:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the left ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the right ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit the entire fimbriated ends of the fallopian tubes (perpendicularly sectioned) and at least 1 representative cross-section, separating left from right&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;lymph-nodes&#34;&gt;Lymph nodes&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For small nodes that will fix well, multiple per cassette submitted in toto &lt;strong&gt;OR&lt;/strong&gt; nodes inked and bisected (so we can tell microscopically which pieces of nodes belong together)&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A good rule of thumb is to bisect lymph nodes if they are &amp;gt; 0.3 cm in greatest dimension&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the node is very fatty, make sure it is sectioned THINLY&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All sentinel lymph nodes need to be sectioned at 2 mm intervals and entirely submitted&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;We often receive sentinel nodes for endometrial cancer. In CoPath, these will be accessioned as a “lymph node, sentinel (GYN)” and have “SNE” on the cassette. The SNE protocol should be indicated on all blocks of lymph node and not on remaining adipose that is submitted.  The protocol and stains should be copied to all additional lymph node blocks in addition to the “SNE” code on the block, but only 1 H&amp;amp;E assigned to the block that the remaining adipose tissue is in (if submitted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit extra fibroadipose tissue (up to 10 cassettes total)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;dictation-template&#34;&gt;Dictation template&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The specimen is received [fresh/for intraoperative consultation/in formalin], labeled &amp;ldquo;[name/MRN/designation]&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indication: Prolapse, leiomyoma, benign</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_benign/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn1/hysterectomy/hyst_benign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;radical-hysterectomy-for-prolapse-leiomyoma-benign&#34;&gt;Radical Hysterectomy for Prolapse, Leiomyoma, Benign&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross description&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Weigh and measure the uterus and cervix and examine the serosa&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orient the uterus (anterior to posterior &#xD;&#xA;&lt;span class=&#34;math math-inline&#34; id=&#34;h-sc-math-0&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/_12819460135120416548.svg&#34; alt=&#34;mathematical expression or equation&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt; RFO [round ligament, fallopian tubes, ovaries]).&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The peritoneum on the anterior uterine surface typically ends higher than on the posterior surface (due to the bladder)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Differentially ink the anterior and posterior resection margins (not the uterine serosa)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Place a probe or forceps into the uterus&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bivalve the uterus into anterior and posterior halves&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Longitudinally section the endocervical canal to examine the transformation zone&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Serially section the uterus at 4 to 5 mm intervals and examine the slices for lesions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Note in gross description if there are fimbriated vs non-fimbriated fallopian tubes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for histology&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;cervix&#34;&gt;Cervix&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Anterior and posterior cervix:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette each, to include squamocolumnar junction&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;uterine-corpus&#34;&gt;Uterine corpus&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Full thickness anterior and posterior endomyometrium, 1 cassette each&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Representative sections of leiomyomas, especially the largest one&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For each leiomyoma &amp;gt; 5 cm without evidence of necrosis or hemorrhage:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 section in 1 cassette&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If none are larger than 5 cm:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit up to 5 cassettes, representatively sampling the lesions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit additional sections from lesions with grossly visible degeneration, hemorrhage, cysts, or necrosis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If hysterectomy/myomectomy is fragmented to the extent that there are no recognizable intact masses:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit 1 section/cassette per 1 cm (up to 10 cassettes)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Representative sections of any intracavitary lesions (polyp, cyst)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If the patient has a history of &lt;strong&gt;BRCA mutation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Lynch syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;abnormal uterine bleeding (AUB)&lt;/strong&gt; and no lesions (polyp, leiomyoma) are present:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit the entire endomyometrium as superficial slices (after taking 1 full-thickness section anterior/posterior)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do not need to submit entire endometrium for a history of breast cancer &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; a gene mutation&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;bilateral-fallopian-tubes-and-ovaries&#34;&gt;Bilateral fallopian tubes and ovaries&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If grossly normal, submit:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the left ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;1 cassette containing the right ovary&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Submit the entire fimbriated ends of the fallopian tubes (perpendicularly sectioned) and at least 1 representative cross-section, separating left from right&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;dictation-template&#34;&gt;Dictation template&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The specimen is received [fresh/for intraoperative consultation/in formalin], labeled &amp;ldquo;[name/MRN/designation]&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Mass</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/ovary_fallopian/no_mass/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/ovary_fallopian/no_mass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ovaries-and-fallopian-tubes-without-masses&#34;&gt;Ovaries and Fallopian Tubes Without Masses&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ovaries and fallopian tubes may be submitted for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As a risk reduction measure because the patient has a germline genetic mutation associated with an increased risk for cancer:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Formal SEE-FIM protocol required:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;BRCA1&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;BRCA2&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Other germline mutation&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not necessary to perform SEE-FIM protocol:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lynch syndrome&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;History of breast cancer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is concern for ectopic pregnancy&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The patient desires permanent contraception&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;risk-reduction&#34;&gt;Risk Reduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Risk reducing salpingo-oophorectomy (RRSO)/prophylactic salpingo-oophorectomy (SEE-FIM Protocol) (usually for BRCA, or other high risk ovarian/breast cancer germline mutation)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovarian Mass</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/ovary_fallopian/ovarian_mass/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/ovary_fallopian/ovarian_mass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-description&#34;&gt;Gross Description&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Measure the size and weigh the specimen. Identify the fallopian tube&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine if the surface is intact, has adhesions, are there any irregularities or protuberances?  Surface lesions must be grossly and microscopically documented.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Open the specimen in a sink to avoid splashing. Note the color and consistency of the contents: watery, bloody, mucoid, fatty, hair etc.  If cystic, is it unilocular or multilocular?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the inner surface. If there are any excrescences or thickened areas of the wall these should be frozen and further sampled for permanents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Note in gross description if fimbriated vs non-fimbriated fallopian tube.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If any of the above is not apparent because the specimen was opened by someone else for intraoperative diagnosis, ask that person.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take gross photos, including a cross section of tumor&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;sections-for-histology&#34;&gt;Sections for Histology:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One section per centimeter of tumor (except mucinous, which needs 2 sections per centimeter). Focus on solid, papillary and cystic areas. State which cassettes contain tumor in relation to ovarian surface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;callout callout-caution d-flex flex-row mt-4 mb-4 pt-4 pe-4 pb-2 ps-3&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;svg&#xA;  xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&#xA;  width=&#34;24&#34;&#xA;  height=&#34;24&#34;&#xA;  viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34;&#xA;  fill=&#34;none&#34;&#xA;  stroke=&#34;currentColor&#34;&#xA;  stroke-width=&#34;2&#34;&#xA;  stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34;&#xA;  stroke-linejoin=&#34;round&#34;&#xA; &#xA; class=&#34;outline/alert-triangle svg-inline callout-icon me-2 mb-3&#34; id=&#34;svg-alert-triangle&#34; role=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;path stroke=&#34;none&#34; d=&#34;M0 0h24v24H0z&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34;/&gt;&#xA;  &lt;path d=&#34;M12 9v4&#34; /&gt;&#xA;  &lt;path d=&#34;M10.363 3.591l-8.106 13.534a1.914 1.914 0 0 0 1.636 2.871h16.214a1.914 1.914 0 0 0 1.636 -2.87l-8.106 -13.536a1.914 1.914 0 0 0 -3.274 0z&#34; /&gt;&#xA;  &lt;path d=&#34;M12 16h.01&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;div class=&#34;callout-content&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;callout-title&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;        &lt;p&gt;Caution&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
