<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Placentas on CU Pathology</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Placentas on CU Pathology</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2024 Richard Revia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Singleton</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/singleton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/singleton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Placentas are sent to us fresh, and formalin added upon receipt in pathology. Please be sure your gross addresses this (“received fresh and subsequently placed in formalin labeled………….)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Placentas with clinical history that mentions post-partum hemorrhage (PPH) and/or manual removal – submit an additional 2 cassettes with 1-2 sections each of basal layer (superficial maternal surface) to look for placenta accreta. These sections should include areas of disruption as well as intact cotyledons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For any placenta with intrauterine fetal demise (IUFD), always submit 10 cassettes – 1 each umbilical cord and membranes (more if you see something unusual, obviously), and the remaining 8 for placental disc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Please be sure to measure placental discs in 3 dimensions. There have been cases where one of the dimensions has been cut off (the report has only shown X x X cm), so I’ve asked the transcriptionists to insert a blank/notify us so that it can be filled in appropriately.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you gross a specimen with a study sticker on the req/container (indicating that the specimen was handled/tissue taken prior to it coming to us), please take a gross photo; they are otherwise handled per our standard procedure. If there is any information on the container or requisition with weight and/or amount of tissue removed by research, please include in your gross.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When you have an (attached) umbilical cord with a &lt;strong&gt;true&lt;/strong&gt; knot, submit your proximal/distal sections in separate cassettes, and designate which is in which cassette. Please take a gross photo of the true knot.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you are grossly concerned for anastomosis of vessels in a multiple gestation placenta, take pictures for documentation&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For a forked cord, state distance to disc edge, can take sections of both forks&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;gross-examination&#34;&gt;Gross Examination&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the membranes and cord:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cord:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How many vessels?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Any nodules on the surface?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thrombi in the vessels?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;TRUE knots?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Membranous or marginal insertion?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hematomas, cysts, aneurysms&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Membranes:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Color (green, brown, pink)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Transparency (can you see the fetal vessels on the chorionic plate clearly? can you read a ruler through the membranes easily?)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nodules? yellow or white?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Insertion into disk: marginal, inside margin (circummarginate), inside margin with prominent fibrin deposition (circumvallate)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;After measurements and examination, cut the cord off at the disc and take two sections of cord (proximal and distal).&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take TWO membrane rolls: one at the site of rupture (if identified) and one elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cut a strip of membranes about 2 cm wide from the most distal portion of the disk. Include a small portion of disk margin. Wrap a &amp;ldquo;jelly roll&amp;rdquo; of membranes. Cut transversely and submit one section from each roll. Once the membrane rolls are done, trim the remaining membranes off the disc and then weigh and measure the disc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the placental disc:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;After the placenta has been weighed, bread loaf the placenta at 1-2 cm intervals perpendicular to the maternal surface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the parenchyma for infarcts, thrombi, cysts, masses, pallor, or other pathology.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the maternal floor for hematomas (fresh or organized) and/or excessive bandlike fibrin.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Examine the fetal surface for discoloration, fibrin, nodules, cysts, or other pathology.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dictate findings including color and texture (red/boggy/beefy, pink/firm, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Any of these abnormalities are what you will want to include in your 3 parenchyma sections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Try to stay away from the edge when taking the parenchymal sections unless it’s the site of a lesion/abnormality.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Take one parenchymal section from at or near the cord insertion site and note in which cassette this is submitted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;singelton-placenta-dictation-template&#34;&gt;Singelton Placenta Dictation Template&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dragon&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;singelton placenta&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twins: fused disc</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/twins_fused/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/twins_fused/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For twin placentas with a &lt;em&gt;fused disc&lt;/em&gt;, it could be:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dichorionic, diamniotic&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Monochorionic, diamniotic&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons we examine these placentas is to determine zygosity from placentation. This is possible only in monochorionic placentation (all monochorionic placentas arise from a single fertilized ova = monozygous; dichorionic placentation can arise from either dizygous or monozygous gestations). Therefore IT IS VERY IMPORTANT TO OBTAIN A GOOD SAMPLE OF DIVIDING MEMBRANES AND A CLEAR GROSS DESCRIPTION!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twins: separate discs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/twins_separate_discs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/placenta/twins_separate_discs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons we examine these placentas is to determine zygosity from placentation. This is possible only in monochorionic placentation (all monochorionic placentas arise from a single fertilized ova = monozygous; dichorionic placentation can arise from either dizygous or monozygous gestations). Therefore IT IS VERY IMPORTANT TO OBTAIN A GOOD SAMPLE OF DIVIDING MEMBRANES AND A CLEAR GROSS DESCRIPTION!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
