<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Products of Conception on CU Pathology</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/products_of_conception/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Products of Conception on CU Pathology</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2024 Richard Revia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/products_of_conception/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Products of Conception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/products_of_conception/products_of_conception/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 12:32:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/grossing/gyn2/products_of_conception/products_of_conception/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;frequently-asked-questions-about-pocs&#34;&gt;Frequently Asked Questions About POCs&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grossing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt; For standard cases with fetal tissue that are not specified as “gross eval only” by the patient, can the attending choose to make the case a gross only?&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, absolutely. In this case, gross photos are required, as this is the only evidence we will have that we examined this case. It is best to check with the attending on service before grossing. As a default, submit a few sections for microscopic review.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt; For cases with fetal and placental tissue that are specified as “gross eval only” by the patient, should we submit placental tissue for microscopic review?&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; This is case dependent and ultimately up to the attending. The “gross eval only” is understood to apply to fetal tissue only. It is best to check the clinical history for any concern for placental pathology and/or to check with the attending on service before grossing. As a default, submit a few sections of placenta for microscopic review.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt; How much detail should be included in the Gross Description of the final report for a case with fetal tissue?&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; This is very much case dependent and attending discretion is required. In certain cases it may be appropriate for the attending to change the gross description to simply read “fetal and placental tissue present”&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reporting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
